Frank Ballard Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Frank Ballard Papers.
undated, 1973-1993.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Ballard, Frank, 1929-.
1 linear foot.
Frank Ballard was a born on 7 December 1929 in Alton, Illinois. He received his B.A. (1952) from Shurtleff College and his M.A. (1953) from the University of Illinois. Ballard was a professor of dramatic arts at the University of Connecticut, retiring in 1989. In 1966, he established the first bachelor of fine arts degree program in puppetry at any American university. A decade later he founded the National Puppetry Institute at the University of Connecticut.
MSS19980193
The collection contains biographical information on Frank Ballard and correspondence, publications, and clippings pertaining to the Puppetry Program at the University of Connecticut.
Biography
Frank Ballard was a born on 7 December 1929 in Alton, Illinois. He received his B.A. (1952) from Shurtleff College and his M.A. (1953) from the University of Illinois. The recipient of numerous awards and honors, Ballard was a professor of dramatic arts at the University of Connecticut, retiring in 1989. In 1966, he established the first bachelor of fine arts degree program in puppetry at any American university. A decade later he founded the National Puppetry Institute at the University of Connecticut.
For more information see Series I: Vitae.
Scope and Content
The collection contains biography information on Frank Ballard and correspondence, publications, and clippings pertaining to the Puppetry Program at the University of Connecticut.
Materials separated from the collection:
Transferred to Archives and Special Collections Periodicals:
Children's Books International 5: Proceedings, 1982.
Transferred to University Archives
The Art of Puppetry in America,William Benton Museum of Art, 1987.
Connecticut Alumnus, v. XLIII, #3-4, 1970
Student Handbook, School of Fine Arts, UConn, 1988-1989.
Threshold: A Report of Creative Concerns at the University of Connecticut, 1982.
UConn Classic, program, 1977.
Transferred to Ballard Puppetry Museum:
A Propos, #16, 1978.
American Puppetry Festival, 1987.
Mime, Mask & Marionette, v. 1, #1-4, 1978.
Nutmeg Puppet News, v. 19, #1-2, 4-5 1992-1993.
Playboard, August 17, 1992.
Punchline, v. XVIII, #5, 1992.
Puppet Life, August 1974, February-March, September-December 1975.
Puppeteers of America
Puppet Festival, 1973.
Festival Nouvelle Orleans, 1974.
Festival 1975.
International Membership Directory, 1976.
37th National Puppetry Festival, 1976.
38th National Festival, 1977.
39th National Festival, 1978.
Southeast Region Puppet Festival, 1985.
40th Annual Festival, 1979.
Puppetry Journal, v. 11, #1-6; v. 12, #2-5; v 13, #1-4, 6; v. 14, #1-3, 6; v. 15, #2-6; v. 16, #2-6; v. 17, #6; v. 18, #1-6; v. 19, #1-5; v. 20, #1-5; v. 21, #1-3, 5-6, v. 22, #1, 3; v. 24, #2-6; v. 25, #1; v. 26, #3; v. 27, #1; v. 30, #5; v. 36, #3, 1985; v. 37, #1-2, 1985; v. 38, #1, 4, 1986-1987; v. 41, #4, 1990; v. 42, #4, 1991; v.44, #2, 1959-1992.
Theatre Crafts, March-April 1975.
The Theatre in Poland, #4 (164), #5 (165) 1972; #12 (195) 1974; #11 (219) 1976.
Arrangement
Series I: Personal Papers ( undated, 1986-1993 )
Series II: Puppetry Program ( undated, 1973-1993 )
Series III: Photographs ( 1987 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
National Puppetry Institute.
Subjects:
Puppet making—Study and teaching.; Puppetry.; Puppets and puppet-plays.; Puppeteers—United States.; Puppet theater in education.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Manuscripts.
Occupations:
Educator.; Puppeteer.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Provenance unknown.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Personal Papers, undated, 1986-1993
  - Honors and Awards, 1986-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript—How to Direct Puppet Theatre, 1987 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Vitae, 1993 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
- Series II: Puppetry Program, undated, 1973-1993
  - Connecticut's Finest, 1988 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1993 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence—Support of Puppetry Program, 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - History of Puppetry Program, 1989-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence—Letters from Children, 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1987-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Articles—Exhibits, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 10)
  - Newsweek on Campus, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 11)
  - Productions
    - Babes in Toyland, 1982 (Box 2:, Folder 12)
    - The Blue Bird, 1984 (Box 2:, Folder 13)
    - The Golden Cockerel, 1977 (Box 2:, Folder 14)
    - H.M.S. Pinafore, 1989 (Box 2:, Folder 15)
    - Kismet, 1975 (Box 2:, Folder 16)
    - Little Shop of Horrors, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
    - The Love for Three Oranges, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
    - The Magic Flute, 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
    - Pippin, 1983 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
    - The Ring of the Nibelung, 1980 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
    - Television
      - From the Top, 1976 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - Puppet Institute and Museum, 1986-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - Puppets at UConn, undated (Box 2:, Folder 24)
  - Weekly Reader articles, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
- Series III: Photographs, 1987
  - Street Fair—Eastbrook Mall, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
  - How to Direct Puppet Theatre images, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 27)